This is your brain thinking and this is
your brain using AI. Over the past year,
I've basically completely replaced
Google. I use Claude to write my morning
briefs, summarize meetings, and even
help me make simple apps that I
otherwise could code myself. But
naturally, as I used more of these
tools, I started to wonder whether or
not it was at the cost of my own
critical thinking abilities. And after
reading what the literature has to say
about this, it's actually not so simple
as AI is just making us dumber. And it's
really the way that you use it that can
change how it affects your brain. So in
this video I want to share what I found
and the habits that you can implement to
help mitigate that. And at the end of
the video I also share with you the
specific ways that I changed the way I
use AI to help mitigate that. The first
thing to answer is is AI making us
dumber? So interestingly when I looked
into this the most relevant papers on
this was even before chat GPT or cloud
came around. So people had this same
concern over 20 years ago when Google
was released. People worried that it
would impact our memories and learning.
So in 2011, researchers conducted a
study where they ran a series of
experiments to see how using Google and
the computer affected people's memories.
So they took a group of participants and
they gave them a list of facts to
remember. For one group, they told them
that they could look it up later on a
computer. And for another group, they
just had to remember it by heart. And
they found three things from this which
they later called the Google effect. The
first is that when people were just
asked regular knowledge questions, they
thought of Google first versus the
actual answer. The second is that when
people knew that they could look it up
later, their memory actually degraded.
And the third was people tended to
remember how to find the piece of
information versus the information
itself. So it's not necessarily that
people got dumber, it's that our brains
default to a more efficient pathway.
rather than remembering the actual
information, it remembers how to get
that information. So if you extrapolate
the study towards LM today, the more we
use AI to not just look up information
but also to help us do tasks or help us
make decisions, the more we are
weakening our own ability to do that and
the more we won't be able to think for
ourselves. I like to think of the brain
as sort of a circuit board where we like
to take the path of least resistance.
People used to just remember by heart
the names of different streets and be
able to drive to places without having
to use an app or a navigation device.
But as we had better technology, we
slowly lost this ability. And now
there's very few people that can
actually do that. If we don't exercise
it and we don't use it, that is really
the danger of LLMs. We're basically
trading productivity and speed for the
ability to think for ourselves. But the
interesting thing that these researchers
found is it's not necessarily a bad
thing depending on how you use it.
There's a term called cognitive
offloading which refers to freeing up
your mental bandwidth so you can focus
on the next level. So there is a real
argument to say that if we use AI in the
right way to free up our cognitive
bandwidth, it gives us a space to think
more deeply about the next level. And
the clearest example of a place you can
cognitively offload are meetings. So for
me, I used to take manual notes during
meetings, which causes me to actually be
less present during the meeting. But now
with these AI tools, it's really easy to
simultaneously have it take notes of the
key information while you are being
fully present in the discussion. And
that's where the sponsor of this video
comes in, Granola. So Granola is
probably one of the best ways I found to
have an automatic workflow to have
summaries with meetings. And before you
think that this is just like any other
AI note-taker, let me explain how it
stands out. So, first, most AI note
takers send a bot to join your call. But
with Granola, the transcription is
invisible. So, you just ask for
permission once from the other person,
and then it's a lot less awkward
throughout the call. And the second
thing is that during the call, you can
still jot down notes or ideas like you
normally would, and at the end of the
call, Granola will synthesize them into
a clean structure summary, and it fills
in everything that you missed. I think
granola AI is genuinely a useful tool
that can help us offload meetings which
probably most of us find to be really
quite draining. And so this gives you
your full attention back for the stuff
that matters. You can try Granola free
at the link in the description or right
here on the screen. But let's get back
to the video. And we probably all think
that we use these tools in that way to
help us work on the next level. But let
me show you what actually happened when
they put this to the test. In 2025, they
did a study where they had people write
essays while relying on chachi. So they
could use chacheti as a writing
assistant to help them think more deeply
about the essays that they were writing.
They took 54 people that were separated
into three groups and they asked them to
write several essays while researchers
used an EEG to look at their brain
activity. The first group they could use
chat GBT in any way that they would
like. The second group, they could use
Google in any way they would like. And
the third group could not use any tools.
They could only write the essay. What
this paper found was that the group that
used CHAGBT had the lowest brain
activation among all groups. And towards
the end, they even just resorted to
copying and pasting. The people who used
ChadBt could barely even remember the
things that they wrote about in their
essays. And when they had that same Chad
GBT group write another essay without
using any tools, their levels of brain
activity was even lower than normal. And
if you compound this over many years, it
could get significantly worse. So the
trap that a lot of people fall into when
they use AI tools is that you think
you're activating critical thinking, but
you're actually not. When we ask a
question and we get an instant response,
our brains think that we sort of thought
of that same response. And this concept
has actually been studied for over two
decades and it's called the illusion of
explanatory depth. For example, if I
asked you if you understood the
mechanism of a zipper, you probably rate
yourself pretty high. And if you read an
explanation, you probably think this
makes perfect sense and I basically knew
that. But if I asked you to explain it
from start to finish how the mechanism
of a zipper works, more likely than not,
you're going to struggle to explain
that. So when we use LLMs to understand
different topics, we get the same
illusion that we're getting smarter that
we're understanding more different
topics. But in reality, the depth of our
understanding is actually quite low
across many different domains. AI
chatbots will write in a way that meets
you at your level. So it will use
analogies that you can understand. It
will use technical terms that you can
understand. But if you think about it
more deeply, when we read a textbook or
a difficult book, we have to pause and
think about what it is the author is
trying to convey. And it is this act of
thinking more deeply that leads us to
understand these topics at a much deeper
level. So what can we actually do about
this? I'm going to share with you how
I've changed the way I use AI. But first
I want to share two different habits
that have nothing to do with AI that can
help you with improving your critical
thinking. And the first is to practice
thinking by having the habit of
journaling. Journaling by pen and paper
is by far one of the best ways to force
yourself to think linearly and also to
write without any external input. You
can't go back and delete different
paragraphs. You can't go and ask an AI
chatbot what you should write about
next. For me, I've been journaling for
nearly a decade now, and I've made a
bunch of videos on this on this channel.
And one of the things I found is that
one of the most valuable ways to journal
is actually not the traditional way of
journaling by writing a daily diary.
When you write a diary, there's actually
very little thinking involved beyond
training your memory. Instead, I would
recommend you to journal about different
ideas that you want to expand on or your
thoughts on things that have happened to
you in your own life. And one thing you
can do as well if you're learning
something is you can easily test your
understanding by journaling about that
topic and writing down everything that
you know about it. By doing this, you
can spot a lot of different gaps in
understanding that you have and it
forces your brain to try and understand
the topics that you're learning far
better. But the second habit to
cultivate your critical thinking is to
invest in skills that compound over
time. And these are things like learning
a language, playing an instrument,
writing essays or creating music. These
type of skills will remain valuable in
the market because there's a time
barrier and a human element to them.
Whereas skills like coding or prompt
engineering, those type of skills will
be commoditized over time. But besides
those two habits, I also want to share
three concrete ways that I've changed
the way I use AI to help improve my
critical thinking. The first is to be
more specific in the way that you use AI
to ask questions. For example, in the
previous video, I showed how I optimized
my workflow using AI. And one workflow I
showed was creating summaries of
extended podcasts and books. And rather
than just having it create a quick
summary, I have it create a extremely
detailed chapter by chapter summary,
which sometimes takes up to 30 minutes
to even read the summary of. As I'm
reading through this, I'm also taking
notes in my personal Obsidian vault,
which has no AI interference. And after
that, I go back and read the original
source, which gives me a much better and
deeper understanding of the book. So I
would also encourage you to go and
create skills and prompts that you use
so that it would encourage you to think
more deeply rather than just
understanding something temporarily. And
that leads to the second thing which is
use AI to think more deeply not just to
finish more tasks. Especially now with
Agentic AI, it's going to be tempting to
just hand off our entire to-do list or
email and have it do everything
automatically. But that's actually a
trap. We might feel more productive per
unit of time, but over the long run, our
productivity will actually decrease. The
reason for that is because we start to
lose context and understanding of our
own decisions. The best way to use these
tools is to use them to help us develop
our own models of understanding and
thinking so that we can make better
decisions for ourselves. So, it's better
to have this separation where you use
these chat models to help you save time
by searching for information or ranking
different things and surfacing it in
front of you and you being the person
that makes the decision always. The
third thing is to not trust these AI
systems. So, don't trust verify. In
2025, Microsoft and Carnegie Melon found
that the more you trust AI, the more
it's correlated with lower rates of
critical thinking. And I think this is
especially important for the next
generation where they are actually
growing up using these models and so
they may never develop this habit or
practice of critical thinking. Just in
my personal experience, even using
frontier models, it's always better to
lean on the side of not trusting the AI
and double-checking anything that it
comes up. Even the best models now,
they'll still occasionally hallucinate
and they'll confidently tell you
something that isn't true and later just
apologize profusely when something
actually goes wrong. like these AI
models can't actually take any
responsibility. So, it's basically a
useless apology. There are some pretty
extreme cases of this where in 2023
there was a lawyer that wrote this
research case using cases that Chad
Gutty provided to him and later on when
he presented it, it turns out every
single case in that research paper was
completely fake and it caused him to
have to pay a significant fine and be at
risk of losing his license. So for me, I
like to treat AI as a extremely
intelligent but non-rustworthy employee.
It can definitely do real work and be
really efficient helping me save time,
but I always make sure I either have it
site its sources or I go and check it
manually. That's why, for instance, I
prefer to use Perplexity when it comes
to doing research with the assistance of
AI models because it is forced to site
everything. So at least you can go and
check the source material. In addition
to not delegating your critical
thinking, you should also not trust the
things that are coming out of it and
verify for yourself. But with all that
being said, I'm optimistic about where
this technology is going. AI use by
itself is not going to make you dumb.
It's how you use it. If you use it
passively, it's going to make you lazy
and not think for yourself. But if you
use it actively and as a way to increase
your thinking and understanding, it can
be an amazing tool. But that's it for
this one. Let me know what you thought
of this video. It's a slightly different
video, a video essay, sort of a new
video format. But I'll see you next
video and let's get it.